so they said the Dhamma is directly
visible hmm no what was it me how is it
comment directly visible because the
Dhamma is founded upon a recognition of
the fundamental characteristics of a
presently enduring experience so the
Dhamma is not a mystical secret the
dummy's discernment of what's already
there in front of you what's already
there in front of you my perception my
feelings my intentions that's already in
front of me
so discerning the nature of those means
seeing the Dhamma hence thumb is always
in the present and Dhamma is always
directly visible it's not that the
Dhamma will come through like oh I have
to be discerning this discerning this
and then I'll discern the Dhamma on some
later occasion on account to discerning
this now you might develop this sermon
on a later occasion account of your
efforts beforehand but efforts
beforehand you can't say that that's
seeing the Dhamma once you see the
Dhamma you saw the Dhamma so unless you
see the Dhamma you should not regard
yourself as somebody we see in the
downline practicing the Dharma while at
the same time knowing I haven't seen the
Dhamma you can your uncie no of course
not because again it's not you doing the
seeing or on seeing it's you discerning
on account of what's there anyway
what on account of things that are there
that cannot not be there in other words
you can discern this so you can want
this so you can choose this but one
thing you cannot do is not perceive and
not have feelings and not have
intentions that's inconceivable you
might want to deny the reason feeling
the reason perception there is an
intention but your acceptance denial
both acceptance and denial
neither acceptance note in our
mystification of it it's all in response
to feeling perception tension that are
there on their own and that's what you
recognize if you study certainly the
Dhamma correctly those are also
indications those things indication
those things indication
buddy of course yeah there are many
different approaches but they would all
be revealing the same principle
presently enduring present there isn't
present enduring things which means you
are secondary to it your sense of
ownership your sense of choice it's all
real but as secondary that's why if you start
but as secondary that's why if you start
seeing your ownership as secondary it
ceases to be on a ship like oh you own
this but I own it more than you do which
means you're not truly the sole ultimate
owner yeah you you you own it more than
everybody else but fundamentally you
don't own it cuz I own it all so you
realize okay so I'm only a relative
owner and as such can you act out of
that ultimate view that you are the
owner that's when the Buddha compared
the general accentuate or even taking of
this body as a borrowing gold and
borrowing jewelry and that you enjoy and
then you forget that it's not yours
that's it yeah you start acting as if
it's yours
and then bailiffs come and knock your
door through and then just start taking
it everything and then you feel
distressed and suffering but that's your
own fault because you forgot they live
as only bother it so and that's that's
the borrowing like perceptions they
really wanted or not feeling is there a
devotee not intentions that ever they
want it or not ignoring that they are
there on their own means you
automatically took them as yours that's
it
but then if you don't take them hey Jose
anymore that's the result of practice
those things are still there exactly
they were never a problem he was you
taking them as yours while they were not
being yours
hence the discrepancy of suffering in
dukkha and this is this way conceiving
that is not more conceiving sure sure
because well conceiving isn't the level
of perception paired with the wrong view
basically the perception of puto Jenna
already conceives so when a petitioner
perceives his perception when he feels
his feelings when he intends his
intentions automatically just by doing
it so to speak
he does it as it's his own his view puts
himself first despite the the evidence
show in the contrary which is no you
have the view you have the attitude
because then these things are there on
their own intuitive so all of you to
join would need to do is stop fueling
that attitude of taking it for granted
as I am the first and start undoing in
his own experience like what am I
feeling right now
I'm feeling I don't know quite
pleasantly sort of related mood okay
that's very good describe the
characteristics and the signs of that
mood to yourself out loud if you want
well the first and obvious thing
whenever we've done this in practicing
with other people the answer would be
it's just there okay so what would be
the signs and characteristics of
something that's just there means it's
kind of independent of you isn't it it's
just there I can move it left I can move
it right I can do this I can do that but
fundamentally I could do any of those
things because this thing is just there
so if something is just there you
haven't created it he was just there you
found it as such but by not thinking
these things boo to Gina just there
means for me means my because I already
am failing to see that I already am and
for me and mine is because this thing is
just there and it's still just there
which means when it ceases to be just
there you won't be able to stand a
second longer
dependently of it so it's really just
about the welding on these
characteristics and knowing how to
question yourself rightly to start
discerning the characteristics of things
that are in the things that's why the
Buddha described a niche and dukkha as
inherent in all these determinations of
your sense of self he didn't say that
Superman let's implement that
impermanent no he said things that
determine you are impermanent things
that determine you are suffering because
of that things that you are are not
yourself things that you are is not you
so to speak cannot be yours and that's
the whole point here you recognize
things they determine you are these
things that are just there so by
dwelling on the themes of
characteristics of things that are just
there you are actually dwelling on the
theme and the characteristics of
impermanence of suffering as in
unsatisfactory this is how it's just
there hmm
is it threatening who blows it I don't
know nobody knows how this came to be
yet it's just there yet my whole
experience is directed upon determined
by it what if this goes that thing
stands a fun to even the thought that he
stands upon that already stands upon
that that the basis of feeling I think
that's already there inclusive up is
inconceivable as you can see exactly so
it's not like you're looking for a great
revelation epiphany
it's just dwelling on those particular
characteristics and that in itself is
going to result in basically diminishing
of the symptoms of known to bailing on
those things by not dwelling on things
just being there by not dwelling on that
impermanence you automatically assume
permanence you automatically assume
ownership by dwelling on that this is
just they're dependent of me kind of
indifferent to me I can react I can do
this but fundamentally I can do any of
it because this thing is enduring on its
own it's earning that more and more means
it's earning that more and more means
discerning the the theme of impermanence
more and more which and automatically
means discerning the theme of this is
more and more dukkha and the results in
the experience of not being taken as
myself so if one has such having views
that say feelings why they do feelings
are there because see you can even you
can even the only reason you're even
able to ask such question why are
feelings it was feeling is there a
during on its own there's no any thought
any response any logical rational turn
is already secondary to this thing being
there that's where Dhamma is beyond thinking
that's where Dhamma is beyond thinking
as an attacker which I cannot be
reasoned doesn't mean it's mystical
means that movements of your reason
cannot stand for that because of which
these movements are cannot stand for the
nature of things which is what Dharma is
but as we showed you can still use these
movements to learn how to look the
opposite direction of the movement to
look at the source of the movement so us
being unison like you only summon a
seeker so you have a for how these
feelings that what is my feeling so
that's a movement that's a rational
question but instead of just trying to
find another rational answer you start
looking for the direction what this
question is pointing it means the fact
that you can ask well what is my current
feeling means the feeling is there your
designation your directing of the
question it would not be possible if the feeling
it would not be possible if the feeling
is not there in doing so you might not
know the particulars of the feeling but
the fact that even in the most ambiguous
terms you know how do I feel now there
is some sense of the direction where the
feeling is but instead of providing the
answer you start looking down that
direction how am I feeling well I'm not
sure okay so that lack of lack of kind
of being not sure how does that feel
then well it kind of feels a bit
depressing what does pressure feel like it's
what does pressure feel like it's
unpleasant
okay so then
me not being sure how I feel slightly
pressure by it means I feel unpleasantly
fundamentally on a subtle level it's
unpleasant what are the characteristics
of that unpleasant feeling that's
present in during why'm while I'm asking
these questions so see like this I said
you use the movements of your question
but you don't follow the direction of
the movement you look at the source let
you learn how to see the background of
that movement the foundation the sauce
which is literally boom often where the
movement came from and that's what the
Buddha meant by only only so yawning is
boom literally so you learn how to
attend the source as opposed to attend
what that sort of question points your
head and that's how you get to discern
more and more characteristics of that
which is already there that feeling is
already there where you want it or not
the mood is already there whether you
want it or not and I talk about the mood
because the mood is kind of a blend
between general perception and general
feeling how you feel it which is
basically the mood is where your mind is
but you can't see directly oh this is my
mood no it's always behind you but if
you never look learn how to look in the
direction from that source you can have
a seat which means you're always going
to be affected by it that's when people
go through their moods like on a daily
basis something down and someone who
doesn't see means they're automatically
affected by this in solitude in solitude
is going to become hard to not see the
signs of your mind which is why people
who exist in the mode of avoiding the
states of them avoiding seeing the state
of the mind but just going with what
direction is offered through their
senses distraction sensuality ill-will
I'm angry I'm sad I'm happy I'm lustful
on this and this and this never stop and
look at the source of it that's why
those people are terrified of Solitude
it feels like drowning literally the
more of existence you go used to the
threshold of being of that barber it's
not being matched that isn't that level
of engagement
the level of sort of a degree of
consciousness in those things and even
you feel like you're drowning that's why
people get panic attacks and anxieties
and dread and overwhelmed baby just by
solitude go mad yeah but you don't go
mad because of the solitude you go mad
on account of not being able to fulfill
the habits of avoiding solitude that
your existential II depend upon that's
why you go man
see if you started doing those habits
you start seeing sorry to this Pleasant
you start seeing bored what boredom is
has a negative connotation neutral
neither Pleasant or unpleasant you start
feeling feeling is lofty and Pleasant
you start delighting in it like boredom
is a neutral feeling from the point of
view of unmatched unmet habits of off
distraction I'm bored because I still assume I must
I'm bored because I still assume I must
be doing something I want to be doing
something but it's nothing I have to do
I can do now or I are nothing that I
particularly want to do some kind of bit
bored you stay with that boredom and then that
you stay with that boredom and then that
is credibly gonna get amplified like
your dependence on needing to do
something including practice meditation
and doing this or what my breath and not
meeting it like on the existential level
of presently during things and that's
when that boredom becomes anxiety and
fear but as I said it's determined by
your dependence on doing things not by
the actual solitude and I'm a neutral
field